Guide to the George Whitmore Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Writings: Fiction, 1959-1989; Series II; 2.71; (8 boxes)
  - Poetry
    - "Natural History," electronic file, undated
      Available through Access Services: Disk #29, file POEM.BAK
    - "On Amtrak," broadside poem published by Free Milk Fund Press, printed version, 1983 (Box 7, Folder 93)
    - Poems 1972, published by Free Milk Fund Press, printed version (2 copies) (Box 8, Folder 94)
    - "The Rock Room," electronic file, undated
    - "To the Sea," published in Montage, printed version, circa 1967 (Box 8, Folder 95)
    - "Tricking," published in The Gay Alternative, typescript photocopy and printed version, 1975 (Box 8, Folder 96)
    - Tricking and Other Poems, published by Free Milk Fund Press, printed version (3 copies), 1974 (Box 8, Folder 97)
    - Untitled Poems, published by Free Milk Fund Press, typescript and printed version (3 copies), 1977 (Box 8, Folder 98)
    - Readings, 1972-1983, undated (Box 8, Folder 99)
    - Miscellaneous poems, typescripts, photocopies, and mimeographs, undated (Box 8, Folder 100)
  - Short stories
    - "Alvah," typescript, notes, correspondence, clippings, 1978-1984 (Box 9, Folder 101)
    - "Bearing Arms," typescript, edited, undated (Box 9, Folder 102)
    - "Betrayal," typescript photocopy, undated (Box 9, Folder 103)
    - "Between the Night," typescript, before 1967 (Box 9, Folder 104)
    - "The Bright Spot," typescript, edited, undated (Box 9, Folder 105)
    - "By Threes," typescript photocopy, undated (Box 9, Folder 106)
    - "The City Stirs," typescript, before 1967 (Box 9, Folder 107)
    - "Clemma," photocopy (from unidentified publication), undated (Box 9, Folder 108)
    - "Confessions of Danny Slocum," published in Christopher Street, 1978-1979
      See novels box 3
    - "Dale's Death," typescript photocopy, undated (Box 9, Folder 109)
    - "The Execution," typescript, before 1967 (Box 9, Folder 110)
    - "Familiar Stranger," typescript, undated (Box 9, Folder 111)
    - "Fathers Day," typescript, 1979 Jun (Box 9, Folder 112)
    - "The Father-Son Act," typescript, undated (Box 9, Folder 113)
    - "Getting Rid of Robert," published in Blueboy, typescript and printed version, undated, 1981 (Box 9, Folder 114)
    - "The Heir Apparent," typescript photocopy, undated (Box 9, Folder 115)
    - "In the File Room," typescript, undated (Box 9, Folder 116)
    - "The Little Minister," typescript, corrected, undated (Box 9, Folder 117)
    - "Mary," electronic file, undated
      Available through Access Services: Disk #27, file MARY
    - "Moving Day," typescript, undated (Box 9, Folder 118)
    - "The Nephew," typescript, undated (Box 9, Folder 119)
    - "The New Coat," published by Free Milk Fund Press, printed version (2 copies), 1981 Dec (Box 9, Folder 120)
    - "No One Gets Hurt," typescript, undated (Box 9, Folder 121)
    - "The Other Woman," typescript, undated (Box 9, Folder 122)
    - "Passing," typescript photocopy, undated (Box 9, Folder 123)
      Whitmore's folder holding this story was labeled "1st draft."
    - "The Reading," typescript, undated (Box 9, Folder 124)
    - "Red Indians," typescript, undated (Box 9, Folder 125)
    - "Le Retour," typescript, undated (Box 9, Folder 126)
    - "Scrabble," published in Christopher Street, typescript and printed versions, 1980 Dec (Box 9, Folder 127)
    - "The Second-Hand Bike," electronic file, undated
      Available through Access Services: Disk #36, files BIKE and BIKE.BAK
    - "Shirt," electronic file, undated
      Available through Access Services: Disk #47, file SHIRT
    - "The Sighting," typescript, undated (Box 9, Folder 128)
    - "Stella Means Star," published in Antidote '65 [student literary magazine of MacMurray College], typescript and issue, 1965 (Box 9, Folder 129)
    - "Sunday Lover," published in Blueboy, printed version, undated (Box 9, Folder 130)
    - "The Transient," published in The MacMurray College Greetings [student newspaper], printed version, 1964 May 9 (Box 9, Folder 131)
    - "Tricking," typescript, undated (Box 9, Folder 132)
    - "Trudy," typescript, photocopy, and two editions published by Free Milk Fund Press, 1982, undated (Box 9, Folder 133)
    - "What Makes Tears," electronic file, undated
      Available through Access Services: Disk #12, file EXCERPT
    - "Out Here: Fire Island Tales"
      - Bound set of stories, with introduction, undated (Box 10, Folder 134)
        Contains "L'Heure Bleu," "The Black Widow," "The Final Public Appearance of Mrs. Senator Coin," "Last Dance," "How to Marry a Zillionaire," "The Guermantes Way," photocopies
      - "The Black Widow," published in Christopher Street, two copies of issue, 1979 Dec (Box 10, Folder 135)
      - "Comes the Dawn," typescript, undated (Box 10, Folder 136)
      - "The Final Public Appearance of Mrs. Senator Coin," typescript, undated (Box 10, Folder 137)
      - "The Guermantes Way," typescript, and printed versions from Drummer 16, undated (Box 10, Folder 138)
      - "L'Heure Bleu," typescript, undated (Box 10, Folder 139)
      - "How to Marry a Zillionaire," published in Alternate, typescript, printed versions, undated (Box 10, Folder 140)
      - "Last Dance," typescript, undated (Box 10, Folder 141)
      - "Out Here," typescript, undated (Box 10, Folder 142)
    - Untitled stories and prose fragments, typescripts, and photocopies, before 1967 (Box 10, Folder 143)
    - Untitled story about the death of a cat (Freddie), undated
      Available through Access Services: Disk #30, file NTS
- Writings: Non-Fiction, General, before 1967-1988; Series III; 0.83; (2 boxes)
  Organized into two subseries: Freelance Projects, and Other Writings.
  The series covers Whitmore's writings in non-fiction, and holds manuscripts, typescripts, printed versions, clippings, correspondence and contracts, with some research materials. It does not include material on his three articles, book, and lecture on the AIDS crisis; these are held in Series IV, Writings on AIDS.
  The Freelance Projects subseries forms the largest part of the series, and contains feature articles, book reviews, and examples of reporting he did as a freelance writer for magazines, newspapers, and newsletters. The files are arranged alphabetically by the title of the periodical that commissioned or paid for the work, though in many cases Whitmore would develop a story idea and pitch it to several different editors. A number of letters and essay samples can also be found by reviewing the electronic files on Disks #43, #45, #46, and #49.
  The subseries Other Writings contains miscellaneous works borne of personal interest: his scholarly writings on Edith Sitwell, Henry David Thoreau, and gay poetry; a biographical film treatment that Whitmore created on Marguerite, Countess of Blessington (1789-1849); an editorial that he published in the New York Times; documentation of presentations he gave on gay culture; and two first-person writings, perhaps autobiographical, about the break-up of a relationship. There is also a single piece of his early career writing, a photocopy of a newsletter from the Citizens Housing & Planning Council. The material is filed alphabetically by title.
  - Freelance projects
    - The Advocate
      - On Dr. Howard Brown, typescript, printed version, clippings, correspondence, 1975-1976 (Box 11, Folder 144)
      - On Labelle (Musical group)
        - Audio recording, 43:21 minutes, 1975 January 18; 1; 00:43:35; There is static and a high amount of buzz on the tape. The program is distorted at times. The program ends abruptly. (Box 11, Item barcode 39002091397019)
          Includes Whitmore's interview with the group in Hartford, Connecticut, on January 18, 1975, and a re-recording of "Black Journal of 'Soul'".
        - Interview, print version, photocopy, 1975 Feb 26 (Box 11, Folder 146)
      - Literature column, clippings, 1975-1976 (Box 11, Folder 147)
      - Miscellaneous articles, clippings and photocopies, 1975 (Box 11, Folder 148)
        Topics include book reviews, profiles of David Rothenberg and the singers Jade and Sarsaparilla, and studies of New York, the Village Voice, and loneliness
    - Alternate, book review, printed version, 1980 Jun (Box 11, Folder 149)
    - Architectural Digest, printed versions, 1985-1986 (Box 11, Folder 150)
      Topics include Ward Bennett, Pamela Banker, William Hodgins, and Jon Bannenberg
    - Art & Antiques, on Spitalfields silks, typescripts, 1984 (Box 11, Folder 151)
      Whitmore's notes and draft available through Access Services: Disk #49, files DEVERE.TXT and SILKS
    - Bay Area Reporter, on William S. Burroughs
      - Interview, audio recording, 47:32 minutes, 1981 Feb 19; 1; 01:35:07; The program begins and ends abruptly. (Box 11, Item barcode 39002091397027)
      - Interview, print version, 1981 Jun 4
    - Berkeley Barb, on gay rights in New York, printed version, 1974 Jun
    - Blueboy, on dating, undated (Box 11, Folder 153)
    - The Body Politic
      - Essays on W. H. Auden, E.M. Forster, typescripts, undated (Box 11, Folder 154)
      - Miscellaneous book reviews, clippings and photocopies, 1978, 1980 (Box 11, Folder 155)
    - Boston Gay Review, book review, printed version, 1978 fall
    - Christopher Street, on sadomasochism, book reviews, printed versions, 1978-1981 (Box 11, Folder 156)
    - Gay Community News, on Gay Activists Alliance, and letter about Andrea Dworkin, printed versions, 1979 Mar 10
    - Gay Sunshine, interviews with Martin Duberman and Tennessee Williams, printed versions, 1977
    - Gaysweek, printed versions and photocopy, 1977-1979 (Box 11, Folder 157)
      Items include book reviews, articles on gay novels and gay theater, and an interview with Edmund White
    - GQ: Gentlemen's Quarterly, on the House of Tweed, printed versions, photocopy, 1988 Feb (Box 11, Folder 158)
      Whitmore's draft and notes are available through Access Services: Disk #46, files TWEEDS and TWEEDS.NTS
    - Harper's Weekly, on gay marriage, printed version, 1975 Sep 1
    - House Beautiful, printed versions and photocopies, 1985-1986 (Box 11, Folder 159)
      Topics include gay couples, London, Florence, and Venice
    - House and Garden, typescript, printed versions and photocopies, 1985-1988 (Box 11, Folder 160)
      Ashbee notes are available through Access Services: Disk #49, file ASHNTS.$$$
      Burrell essay is available through Access Services: Disk #43, file BURRELL
      Monaghan draft is available through Access Services: Disk #49, file MONAGHAN
      Letters to Shelly Wanger are available through Access Services: Disk #28, file BEIGE, and Disk #46, file SHELLY
      Topics include C.R. Ashbee, Sir William Burrell, Margot Johnson, and Tom Monaghan
    - Manhattan, inc., typescript, printed versions, and photocopies, 1985-1987 (Box 11, Folder 161)
      Part of the Rambusch text is available through Access Services: Disk #49, file RAMBTXT2
      Topic include the Museum of Broadcasting, Rambusch Decorating Company, Pierre Deux, the Aesthetic movement, United States Postal Service, and Modernist decorative arts
    - New York Times, on Bewley's cafes and Irish tea, printed versions, clippings, photocopies, correspondence, 1983 (Box 11, Folder 162)
    - Pan Am Clipper, printed version, correspondence, 1985 -1987 (Box 11, Folder 163)
      Notes and draft for London taxis is available through Access Services, Disk #45, files CAB and CABTXT
      Topics include British country houses, Palladian villas, London taxis
    - Seaport, printed versions and photocopy, 1985, undated (Box 11, Folder 164)
      Topics include the Old Merchants House and Washington Market
    - 7 Days, on Andy Warhol, typescript and printed version, 1988 Apr 27 (Box 11, Folder 165)
    - SIECUS Report, on books about gays, issue, 1978 Jul (Box 11, Folder 166)
    - SoHo Weekly News, on New York street life, and the Catholic Church, printed versions and photocopies, 1975
    - Travel and Leisure
      - On the Cheltenham Spa, typescript, research material, 1984 (Box 11, Folder 167)
      - On the Dorset Square Hotel, typescript, correspondence, research material, 1986-1987 (Box 11, Folder 168)
      - Miscellaneous articles, printed versions, clippings, correspondence, photocopies, 1983-1988 (Box 11, Folder 169)
        The Galveston essays are available through Access Services: Disk #45, files GALV and GALV2
        Topics include Dublin, Georgian architecture, Annapolis, Cripple Creek, blockbuster museum exhibitions, exhibition designers, and Galveston
    - United, on Pearl and Albert Nipon, printed versions and photocopies, 1983 Jun (Box 11, Folder 170)
    - Village Voice
      - "The Fire Last Time," correspondence, drafts, article clipping, photocopies, 1977-1987 (Box 12, Folder 171)
        Whitmore's article on the Everard Baths fire was published in the Village Voice August 11, 1987; folder includes drafts of "The Siamese Connection," and correspondence with New York Times and Advocate editors. His extensive research files on the fire are in Series IV.
      - "New Faces: John Kelly," typescript carbon, notes, printed version, photocopy, 1988 (Box 12, Folder 172)
        Electronic file available through Access Services: Disk #28, file KELLY
    - Vogue, on art auctions, printed versions and photocopies, 1986 (Box 12, Folder 173)
    - Washington Post Book World, review of gay books, clippings, 1978 Jan 8 (Box 12, Folder 174)
    - WIN, on the gay rights bill, issue and photocopy, 1974 Jul 4 (Box 12, Folder 175)
    - Unidentified publisher, on Houghton Hall, Norfolk, England, electronic files, 1985
      Available through Access Services: Disk #36, files HOUGHTON, LADYCINT, LADYCQUO, LADYCTXT
      Includes the transcript of an interview with Sybil Sassoon, Marchioness of Cholmondeley (1894-1989), July 18, 1985
    - Unidentified newspaper, on the gay rights bill, clipping, 1975 Oct 8 (Box 12, Folder 176)
  - Other Writings
    - Citizens Housing & Planning Council newsletter, photocopy, 1974 Sep (Box 12, Folder 177)
    - "Edith Sitwell's 'The Canticle of the Rose': An Explication of the Text," [in Speech Magazine ?], typescript, galley, before 1967 (Box 12, Folder 178)
    - "Friendship in New England: Henry Thoreau"
      - Thoreau and Melville paper, mimeograph, 1974 (Box 12, Folder 179)
        Paper presented at the second annual Gay Academic Union conference, and at the Modern Language Association; folder includes a printed GAU conference program, and Whitmore's critique of the event.
      - Essay for Gai Saber, parts one and two, typescript, undated (Box 12, Folder 180-181)
      - Issues of Gai Saber, volume 1, numbers 2 and 3-4, 1977-1978 (Box 12, Folder 182)
    - "Love Songs for the Extra-terrestrials: Should There Be a Metaphysic for Gay Poetry?" in The Gay Alternative, no. 11, printed version, 1976 (Box 12, Folder 183)
    - "Marguerite: The Life of Lady Blessington," typescript of proposed film treatment, 1985, undated (Box 12, Folder 184)
    - "Patrimony and Fraternity in Gay Male Poetry," paper presented at Gays at Penn, University of Pennsylvania, typescript, correspondence, ephemera, 1976 Jan-Mar (Box 12, Folder 185)
    - "We Wished We Had a Knife," editorial published in the New York Times, photocopy, 1979 Sep 20 (Box 12, Folder 186)
    - Untitled presentation on "the first stages of coming out," given at the Gay Academic Union symposium, typescript photocopy, 1974 Feb 22 (Box 12, Folder 187)
    - Untitled presentation on "gay culture" given at Gay Activists Alliance Gay Liberation Forum, ephemera, clipping, 1976 Feb (Box 12, Folder 188)
    - Miscellaneous writings (possibly autobiographical), typescripts, 1977, undated (Box 12, Folder 189)
- Writings on AIDS, 1984-1989; Series IV; 1.25; (3 boxes)
  Arranged by project title, and filed chronologically by date.
  Whitmore wrote three interrelated articles, one book, and one lecture on the topic of AIDS and the daily lives of its victims. Due to the volume of material involved, these files were organized into a single series. Folders here hold correspondence, contracts, text drafts, page proofs, and printed versions. Also here are Whitmore's research files including transcripts of interviews held with AIDS patients, family members, and care givers, consent forms signed by the interviewees, and folders of fan mail that Whitmore received for three of the projects.
  In late 1984 Whitmore pitched an idea to the editor of The New York Times Magazine: an article that would focus on an AIDS patient's relationship with his crisis intervention counselor. Whitmore then worked closely with the Gay Men's Heath Crisis to find appropriate subjects who would agree to have their personal lives made public. "Reaching Out to Someone with AIDS," the story of James Sharp and his advocate Edward Dunn, was published in the magazine on Sunday, May 19, 1985; an offprint was issued afterward by the GMHC and used for fund-raising purposes.
  His second article, a first-person essay titled "Someone Was Here: A Gay Man Confronts AIDS," was published in GQ ( Gentlemen's Quarterly ) in April 1986.
  Whitmore's book, Someone Was Here: Profiles in the AIDS Epidemic, was published by New American Library in the spring of 1988. It expanded upon his earlier work on Sharp and Dunn by adding to it the stories of a Colorado AIDS patient and his family, and a group of patients and care-givers at Lincoln Hospital in the Bronx borough of New York City. The book's epilogue was published in advance of the book. That essay, titled "Bearing Witness," appeared in the Sunday, January 31, 1988, issue of The New York Times Magazine.
  The series ends with a folder documenting a presentation on AIDS and identity that Whitmore made at the Brooklyn College Humanities Institute in April 1988.
  The electronic files for some of these projects are held in Series VI, on Disks #1 through #11, #16 through #23, and #41. Readers may view these files by applying to the library's Access Services desk.
  - "Reaching Out to Someone with AIDS" (working title: "Living with AIDS")
    Electronic files documenting the research for, and composition of, the article are available through Access Services, Disks #8-11 and #18
    - Correspondence, 1984-1985 (Box 13, Folder 190)
    - "Living with AIDS," typescript carbon (2 copies, one corrected), 1985 (Box 13, Folder 191)
    - Research files and interviews
      - Dunn, Edward, 1985 (Box 13, Folder 192)
      - General notes, 1984-1986 (Box 13, Folder 193)
      - Jacoby, Tom, 1985 (Box 13, Folder 194)
      - Lanzaratta, Philip, 1984 (Box 13, Folder 195)
      - Sharp, Jim, 1985-1987 (Box 13, Folder 196-197)
    - Fan mail, 1985 May (Box 13, Folder 198)
    - Reprints, published by Gay Men's Heath Crisis, 1985 (Box 13, Folder 199)
  - "Someone Was Here," correspondence, contract, article photocopies, 1985-1986 (Box 13, Folder 200)
    Electronic files documenting the research for, and composition of, the article are available through Access Services, Disk #17
  - "Bearing Witness" (working title: "The Heart Keeps Beating")
    - Correspondence, contract, 1987 (Box 13, Folder 201)
    - "The Heart Keeps Beating," typescript carbon (2 copies), with wire release printout, 1987-1988 (Box 13, Folder 202)
    - "The Heart Keeps Beating," electronic file, 1988
      Available through Access Services, Disk #41, file TIMES.ART
    - Untitled draft, computer printout, corrected, and proof sheets, 1988 Jan
    - Fan mail, 1988 (Box 13, Folder 203-205)
    - Article photocopies, 1988 (Box 13, Folder 206)
  - Someone Was Here: Profiles in the AIDS Epidemic
    Electronic files documenting the research, composition, and promotion of the book are available through Access Services, Disks #1-7, #16-17, #19-23, and #41. Paper versions may exist in the folders listed below.
    - Contract, correspondence, book jacket and cover, 1985-1987 (Box 14, Folder 207)
    - Book manuscripts
      - Typescript, undated (Box 14, Folder 208-210)
      - Typescript photocopy, bound, 1988, undated (Box 14, Folder 211)
      - Typescript photocopy, corrected, undated (Box 14, Folder 212-214)
    - Research files and interview notes
      - AIDS statistics, 1985-1987 (Box 15, Folder 215)
      - Consent forms, 1985-1988 (Box 15, Folder 216)
      - Detroit, 1987 (Box 15, Folder 217)
      - Heavener, Hattie, correspondence and interview, 1987 (Box 15, Folder 218)
      - Jacobs, Paul, 1984, undated (Box 15, Folder 219)
      - Lincoln Hospital
        - Baez, Carmen, interview, 1987 (Box 15, Folder 220)
        - Whalen, Fran, interview, 1987 (Box 15, Folder 221)
        - General notes, 1987 (Box 15, Folder 222-223)
      - Maes, Michael
        - Correspondence, notes, and interviews, 1986-1987 (Box 15, Folder 224)
        - Medical and personal records, 1986-1987 (Box 15, Folder 225)
        - Rocha, Manuela, interview, 1987 (Box 15, Folder 226)
      - Reviews, 1988-1989 (Box 15, Folder 227)
      - Fan mail, 1988 (Box 15, Folder 228)
    - Untitled presentation on "AIDS and identity" given at the Brooklyn College Humanities Institute; lecture notes on index cards, correspondence, ephemera, 1988 Apr (Box 15, Folder 229)
- Subject Files, 1973-1988; Series V; 0.42; (1 box)
  The series holds material kept by Whitmore on a number of topics related to his writings, primarily those of his freelance assignments. Most folders hold brochures, newspaper clippings, maps, and miscellaneous tourist literature, but a few also have pieces of correspondence. Whitmore's research materials on the Everard Baths include an audio recording of his 51-minute interview with fire investigators. The file on Scotland contains two of Whitmore's story ideas in typescript. All literature concerning AIDS is filed in Series I and Series IV.
  - Art, 1988 (Box 16, Folder 230)
  - Burroughs, William S., 1981 Feb 18
  - Civilian Conservation Corps, 1978-1983 (Box 16, Folder 231)
    Includes correspondence from Whitmore's mother and others, and a section from Lowell Whitmore's memoir describing his CCC service
  - England
    - Country houses, 1981-1985 (Box 16, Folder 232-233)
      Includes guidebooks for Blenheim, Boughton, Bowhill, Brighton, Burghley, Chatsworth, Drumlanrig, Harewood, Ickworth, Petworth, and Wilton
    - Miscellaneous material and maps, 1987-1988 (Box 16, Folder 234)
  - Everard Baths fire
    - Audio recording of interview with unidentified investigators, 51.22 minutes, undated; 1; 00:51:12; There is high background noise on the tape. (Box 16, Item barcode 39002091397035)
    - Print materials and notes, 1977-1982 (Box 16, Folder 235-236)
  - Homosexuality, homosexual literature, 1973-1980, undated (Box 16, Folder 237)
    Includes two graphic publications, Stonewall Romances (1979) and Gay Comix (1980)
  - Ireland
    - General information, circa 1983, 1987 (Box 17, Folder 238)
    - Trinity College Dublin, circa 1983 (Box 17, Folder 239)
    - Wexford, 1988 (Box 17, Folder 240)
  - Italy
    - Correspondence, receipts, 1986 (Box 17, Folder 241)
    - Tourist literature and maps, circa 1986, 1988 (Box 17, Folder 242)
  - Scotland, Glasgow, 1984, undated (Box 17, Folder 243)
    Whitmore's essays are available through Access Services: Disk #43, files GLASCOW [sic] and TENEMENT
    Includes Whitmore's proposals for articles on the city and the Tenement Museum.
  - Varnedoe, Kirk, 1986, 1988 (Box 17, Folder 244)
- Electronic Files, 1981-1986; Series VI
  Arranged in order by disk number.
  Box 18 holds restricted material that may be seen only with permission of the curator.